<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaracyon and power of the Chrysten fayth</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109151</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844801</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844801</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9646</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18645)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9646)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 30:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaracyon and power of the Chrysten fayth</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1545?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustration on title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C⁶.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained; some leaves torn at corners, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9646:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9646:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶The declaracyon and power of the Chryſten fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the scourging of Christ</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <q>¶He that beleueth on me, hath euerlaſtynge lyfe. <bibl>Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .vj.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:9646:2"/>
            <q>¶Here worketh in the beleuynge man fayth thorowe loue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good workes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che God hath ordeyned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entent that we ſhulde walke therin. <bibl>Ephe. ij.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>¶He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loueth his neyghboure as hym ſelfe, kepeth all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of god. <bibl>Mat. vij.</bibl> 
               <bibl>Rom. xiij.</bibl> 
               <bibl>Gala. v.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>¶This is the victory y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the world, our Beleue .i. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .v. For Chryſt ſaith, be of good chere I haue ouercome the worlde. <bibl>Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xvj.</bibl>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶worlde.</head>
               <q>¶All y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in the worlde is the luſt of the fleſſhe the luſt of the iyes, and the pryde of goodes <bibl>.i. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .ii.</bibl> and he that ſoweth in his fleſſhe, ſhall of the fleſſhe repe corrupcyon. <bibl>Gala. vii.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Fleſſhe, blode.</head>
               <q>¶Fleſſhe and blode ſhall not inheryte the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedom of god <bibl>.i. Cor. xv. Chap y.</bibl> For the fleſſhe luſteth contrary to the ſpyryte. <bibl>Gala. Ca.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Deuyll.</head>
               <q>¶Your aduerſary the deuyll as a rorynge lyon w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lketh aboute, ſekynge who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuoure <bibl>i. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e. v. Ca.</bibl> Chryſte hath put downe hym that h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> fordeſhyp ouer deathe, that is to ſay the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. <bibl>Heb. ii. Ca. C.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="religious_tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:9646:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as muche as the holy Scrypture / is a mooſte precyous Iuwell / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth thorowe grace, vnto them whiche receaue it in fayth, thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, the whiche doth teache, and leade vs to that euerlaſtynge lyfe, which word alſo is very Cihyſt hym ſelfe. Now he that entreth not in by this dore into the ſhepe folde, but clymeth vp ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, the ſame is a thefe and a rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. I am ſayth Chryſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe, and the lyfe, euery one that beleueth on me, hath euerlaſtynge lyfe. Thus muſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> euery true chryſten, ſpryng out of chriſt folowing his fote ſteppes in thy lyuinge or els it can not appere that Chryſt abi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth in the, &amp; thou in hym, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch in the vyne, or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good tree, for yf that thou (lyke vnto the good tree Chryſte, bryngeth not forth good fruyte, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>we hym in teachynge, ſufferynge, and
<pb facs="tcp:9646:3"/> to make ſhort in all thy lyuynge, ſo canſt thou not be of his flocke, for all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in chriſt, doth folowe chriſt, in theyr liuing.</p>
            <p>THe worlde ſayeth that they knowe god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr good workes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is none other, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preceptes of men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they teache, and obſerue, for that call they goddes ſeruys, but it is nothyng ſo they vnderſtande not what they ſpeake, neyther wherof they affyrme, which are but me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes fables, and with them turne they men from the truth, but the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of god ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not in wordes, but in power. Why make ye your booſte of me (ſayth chriſt) &amp; ſay, Lorde, Lorde, and do not that which I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund you, not one of you, that ſay vnto me Lorde / lord ſhall come vnto me, but they that do my fathers wyll which is in heauen, that is what ſoeuer ye wolde that men ſhulde do to you, euen ſo do to them, for this is the lawes and the prophetes. He that he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth my worde, and doth not there aft<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9646:3"/> is lyke vnto a very foole. I am the vyne, and ye are the braunches, he that aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in me, and I in hym, the ſame bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth forth moch frute? wylt thou know ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what maner of fruytes Chriſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth? Verely the fruytes of the ſpryte, the whiche is loue, ioye, peace, long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge, gentlenes, all goodnes, faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, mekenes, temperancye, ryghtwyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and trueth. Who ſoeuer is voyde of theſe and foloweth not them, ſo is he no tree of the holy ſpyryte, nor yet none of his pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ttes, although he be byſſhop doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, parſon. &amp;c. ye although he can prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and teache, &amp; prate neuer ſo goodly of the ſcrypture. For ſo longe as he folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not theſe fruytes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyryte with his lyuynge dyſceaueth hym ſelfe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he thynketh and ſayeth that he beleueth in Chriſt and is a chryſtian, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe he is not in Chryſte, but far wyde of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, lyke vnto thoſe Iewes which ſayde they were the ſede of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am, but Chryſte ſayd that they were of
<pb facs="tcp:9646:4"/> thjeyr father y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl, euen ſo are all they the chyldren of the deuyll, &amp; in darkenes, and be yet in the olde vnfruytefull tre of Adam, ſo longe as we brynge not forth theſe true fruytes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpryte, althoughe we faſt, praye, &amp; do neuer ſo moche it can not help vs, ſo longe as we deny hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our dedes, &amp; are abhomynable, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyent to god, and his holy worde.</p>
            <p>THerfore derely beloued, it is moſte nedefull for vs, fyrſte with a repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge herte to be conuerted to God and his worde, and to edefy oure ſelues with the moſte holy fayth that is in our lorde Chryſt for the remyſſyon of ſynnes. And ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darely to loue our bretherne, for our heauenly fathers ſake (bycauſe they be created after his ymage) and for our lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de &amp; mayſter Chryſtes ſake, which ſayth loue ye one another, lyke as I haue lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued you. And alſo bycauſe they be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of his precyous blode. And thyrdely <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> longe and hope for the lyfe to come <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9646:4"/> cauſe this lyfe can not be leade without ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. Theſe thre poyntꝭ (I meane fayth, loue, and hope) are the profeſſion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygyon of a chriſten man, the which god thorowe his ſpyryte marketh all that be his immediatly, and as ſoone as they be ioyned to Chryſt, and made membres of his churche, therfore ſayeth Chriſt to all faythfull. Mat. v. Let your lyght ſo ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne before men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they maye ſe your good workes, and gloryfy your father whiche is in heuen, lyke as you may ſe in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, howe that fayth worketh thorowe loue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of mercy, which is the offyce of loue, to powre out agayn the ſame goodneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe hath receyued of God vpon her neyghboure, and to be to her, as ſhe fealeth Chryſte to her ſelfe. The offyce of loue is onely to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and to bere with his neyghbour the burdayne of his infyrmytyes, for he that loueth his brother, abydeth in the lyght, &amp; there is none offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge in hym, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is redy alwayes to help hym, yee we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:9646:5"/> it his ennemye. And thoſe men be the true chryſten and moſte happy. Chryſte ſayth. Math. v. Bleſſyd are the mercyful for they ſhall obtayne mercye. Loo, here god hath made a couenaunt with vs, to be mercyful vnto vs, yf we wyl be mercy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full one to another, ſo that the man whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſheweth mercy vnto his neyghbour may be bolde to truſt in God for mercye in all nedes (for loue holdeth all a lyke, the ryche &amp; the poore, the frende and the foo, the thankefull and vnthankeful, the kynſemen and ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger.) So nowe yf he that ſheweth no mercye truſt in God for mercye, his fayth is fleſſhely &amp; worldely, for God hath promyſed mercye onely to the mercyful. And therfore the mercyles ſhall haue iudgement without mercye. wherfore yf thyne ennemy hunger, fede hym, yf he thruſte gyue hym drynke. &amp;c. Roma. xij. Go to then and deſyre god to prynte this profeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſten fayth on thyne herte, and to encreaſe it daylye more and more, that thou mayeſt be fu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9646:5"/> ſhapen lyke vnto the ymage of Chryſt in knowlege and loue, for that is good and accepted in the ſight of god our ſauyour whiche wyll haue all men ſaued, and to come vnto the knowledge of the truthe. ¶Nowe that all men ſhulde the better vnderſtande all trewe chryſten, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che muſt fyrſte haue a ſtedfaſt fayth an truſt in almyghty god to obtayne al the mercye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath promyſed vs, thorowe the deſeruynge and merytes of Chryſtes blode onely. And ſecondarely muſt he for ſake all euyll, and tourne to God to kepe his wayes, &amp; to fyght agaynſt hym ſelfe and his corrupte nature ꝑpetually, that he may do the wyl of god euery day bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and better. For fayth in God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thorowe our lorde Ieſus Chryſt ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge to the couenauntes &amp; appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tement made betwene god and vs is our ſaluacyon. Further ye maye ſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge from God vnto the beleuynge man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers fruytes of the holy ſpyryte, for you <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are borne a new,
<pb facs="tcp:9646:6"/> not of mortall ſede, but of immortall by the worde of god, whiche is ſent vs from heauen. Iacobi .i. Euery good gyft, and euery perfyt gyft is from aboue, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth downe from the father of light, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whome is no veryablenes, neyther is he chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vnto darkenes. And alſo. Ro. v. ſayinge the loue of god is ſhed abrode in oure hertes by the holy Ghoſte, for the fruytes of the ſpyryte is in all goodnes, rightwyſneſſe, &amp; trueth. Ephe. v. Gal. v. and agaynſt ſuch there is no lawe, for yf we mortyfye the dedes of our bodyes by the helpe of the ſpyryte we ſhall lyue, and as many as are led by the ſpryte of God, they are the ſones of God. For we haue not receyued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpryte of bondage to fere any more, but we haue receyued the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte of adopcyon, wherby we crye Abba father. The ſame ſpyryte certyfyeth our ſprite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are the ſones of god. Ro. viij.</p>
            <p>ANd aſo as the holy ſcrypture ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that fayth, hope, pacye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ry<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9646:6"/> wylnes, peace, &amp; loue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ſygnes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of the fruyte that ſpryngeth of tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe vertues, as fayth a herte bycauſe the beleue of the herte iuſtyfyeth. &amp;c. Ro. x. And God maketh the hert pure thorowe beleue. Act. x. whiche beleue worketh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the wyll of God, for by grace are we made ſaufe, thorowe fayth, and that not of our ſelues, for it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyfte of god and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not thorow workes, leſt a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> man ſhuld boſte hym ſelfe, for we are h<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> workemanſhyp created in Chryſte Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vnto good workes. Ephe. ij. For a good man out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good treaſure of his herte bryngeth forthe good thynges, for it is not poſſyble to pleaſe God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out fayth. Hebre. xj.</p>
            <p>ALſo Hope hath heuen bycauſe that the chryſtens hope is onely in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, lokynge &amp; abydynge pacyently after that thynge that is promyſed to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome onely thorowe the grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of god, as we hope after euerlaſtynge
<pb facs="tcp:9646:7"/> ioy, whiche Chryſte hath promyſed vnto all that beleue and haue ſtedfaſt hope in hym (ſayinge) feare not lytle flocke, for it is your fathers pleaſure, to gyue you a kyngedome. Luc. xij. Therfore do we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in hope. Ro. xij. whiche rycheſſe is Chryſte in you, the hope of glorye. Col. j. For and we reioyce in the true hope (whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of fayth) and do fele the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe of goddes mercy within our hertꝭ, then althoughe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe wold vs ſtrayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condempe, and that hell alſo wolde vs deuoure, and all ſynne withall our enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes wolde fall vpon vs, yet ſhall they all haue no power ouer vs, yf that oure perfyt hope &amp; truſt be in god, &amp; marke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge fayth, what Chriſt onely thorowe his bytter death hath deſerued for vs.</p>
            <p>ALſo Pacyence hath a ſcourge, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the chryſten hath alwayes in the worlde trybulacyons, afflyccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, neceſſyte, anguyſſhe, ſtrypes. &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whiche he reioyſeth greatly. Ro. v.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9646:7"/> the father of mercy comforteth them in all theyr perſecucyons, for vnto you it is gyuen that not onely ye ſhulde beleue on chryſt, but alſo ſuffre for his ſake. Phi. j. Thus all that wyll lyue godly in Chryſt Ieſu muſt ſuffre perſecucyons. ij. Ti. iij. for trybulacyon bryngeth pacyence, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyence bryngeth experyence. Ro. v. let pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyence therfore haue her perfyt worke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye maye be perfyt &amp; ſounde, for they that are Chryſtes haue crucyfyed the fleſſhe with the appetytes and luſtes. Ga. v. bi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaynt Peter ſayeth .j.iiij. ſe that none of you ſuffre as a murtherer, or a theſe, or an euyl doer, but yf any man ſuffre as a chriſten man, let hym not beſhamed, but lette hym gloryfye God on this behalfe. Oure lorde ſayeth, in the worlde ſhall ye haue trybulacyon, but be of good chere I haue ouercome the worlde. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xvj. Therfore can no man enter in to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers kyngedom, but thorowe manyfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de temptacyons, as our Lorde with his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poſtles be, that we folowynge theym
<pb facs="tcp:9646:8"/> nyght be founde vnto laude, glory, and honour, at the aperynge of Ieſu Chryſt our Lorde .i. Pet. i.</p>
            <p>FVrther ryghtwyſnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chryſt, which alſo hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed it to all his elect, thorowe perfyte fayth in his blode, ſaying, bleſſed ar they which ſuffre ꝑſecucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ryghtwyſenes <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, for theyrs is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdome of heuen. <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r chryſte onely is our ryghtwyſeneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, to iuſtify all that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleue .i. Co. i. Ro. ix.x. You muſt marke <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat there is two maner of ryghtwyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, the which be workes &amp; faith. Nowe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ryghtwyſenes of workes is, when a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an without fayth, thorowe Ipocreſy <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yll fulfyll with his workes the lawe of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, lyke vnto the Phareſies. Luc. xviii.</p>
            <p>ALſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites had a ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to godwarde, but it was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rdynge to knowlege, for they were (ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as the moſt parte of vs nowe are) v<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:9646:8"/> ygnorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ryghtwyſnes of god and therfore are not obedient therunto bycauſe we ſeke it not by fayth, but as it were by our good workes, lyke vnto the learned of the ſcripture &amp; the Phariſies. Luc. v. To whome Chryſte ſayde, I cam not to call the ryghtwyſe, but ſynners to repentaunce. Therfore the holy Ghoſte ſhal rebuke the worlde of ryghtwyſnes. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xix. bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world wyll be made ryghtwyſe by theyr good workes, but ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ryghtwyſnes excede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſnes of the learned of the ſcryptures. Pharyſies you can not enter in to the kyngdom of heuen. And ſecondarely, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men be not vpryght in all theyr handelynge and lyuynge, for all men do corrupte theyr wayes on the earthe, lyke as dyd man before the floude of Noe, for in what maner of byinge, or ſellynge is there nowe without deceyte, lyinge, and vnryghtwyſnes, yee what maner of peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple is there in the worlde, ryche, or pore, ſpyrytuall, or temporall, that doth his
<pb facs="tcp:9646:9"/> offyce truely, and vpryghtely, do you thynke that the holy Ghoſte wyll not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke you, yes be ye ſure for all vnryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſnes is ſynne .i. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .v. God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſayinge, ye ſhall not ſteale, neyther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, neyther deale falſely one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> another, ye ſhall do no vnryghtuouſnes in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neyther in meteyarde, weyght, or meaſure. &amp;c. Leuit. xix. For who ſoeuer doth not rightuous is not of god, but of the deuyll .i. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .iii. Nowe ſayth chriſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſſyd are they whiche hunger &amp; thurſt for ryghtwyſnes, for they ſhall be fylled. Therfore he that thynketh to be made ryghtwyſe by chryſt, muſt haue luſt to ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue an vpryght lyfe before god, &amp; be poore in herte, ſekynge moſte ſpecyally y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, and the ryghtwyſneſſe therof, for the ryghtwyſneſſe no doubte, which is good before god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of the fayth of Ieſus Chryſt, vnto all, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleue. Ro. iij. For no man thorowe his owne good dedes can be made right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe. Gala. ij.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9646:9"/>
            <p>ALſo to haue peace, whiche ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth &amp; conſumeth wrathe, enuy &amp; malyce. Therfore the deuyl our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary (ſynce that peace was made by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene God and man thorowe Chryſte) hath no more power ouer our ſoules, for yf the peace of God rule in our hertꝭ, the whiche paſſeth all vnderſtandynge. Phi. iiij. To the whiche peace we are called. Col. iij. then is our conſcience fylled with great ioy, hauynge abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunce of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall goodneſſe, bycauſe our ſauyoure Chryſt hath pacyfyed the father, &amp; hath made an atonement for vs, and for all our myſdedes. For he is oure peace whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath put awaye, thorowe his fleſſhe the cauſe of hatred, &amp; ſo makynge peace hath reconcyled vs to God thorowe his croſſe, and ſlew hatred therby, and came and preached peace vnto vs, for thorowe hym we haue an open way in, in one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father. Ephe. ij. peace I leue <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith you (ſayth Chryſt) my peace I gyue <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to you. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xiij. Let vs therfore for
<pb facs="tcp:9646:10"/> lowe thoſe thyngꝭ whiche make for pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, &amp; thynges wherwith one maye edyfy another. Ro. xiiij. For theſe wordes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue I ſpoken vnto you (ſayth Chryſt) that in me ye myght haue peace. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xvj.</p>
            <p>THe laſte &amp; pryncypall is loue, other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe called charite, bycauſe loue is a great and a pryncypall vertue aboue all other. For thoughe I dyd ſpeke with the tonges of men and aungels, and yet had no loue I were as a ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng braſſe, or as a tynklynge cymball, and thoughe I coulde prophecye and vnderſtande all ſecretes, &amp; had all knowlege, &amp; all fayth, ſo that I coulde moue mountaynes out of theyr places, &amp; yet had no loue I were nothynge. And thoughe I beſtowed all my goodes to fede the pore, and though I gaue my body euen that I burned, &amp; yet had no loue, it profyteth me nothyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. &amp;c. i. Cor. xiij. For he that hath perfyt loue, fulfylleth the hole lawe. Ro. xiij. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Chryſt ſayth. A newe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundem<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9646:10"/> gyue I vnto you, that ye loue togyther as I haue loued you, that euen ſo ye lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue one another. By this ſhall all men knowe that ye ar my diſciples, yf ye ſhall haue loue one to another. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xiij. He that hath my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes and ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth theym, the ſame is he that loueth me, and he that loued me, ſhall be loued of my father, and I wyll loue hym, &amp; we wyl come vnto hym, and wyll dwel with hym. For God is loue, and he that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in loue, dwelleth in God, and God in hym .j. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .iiij.</p>
            <p>FOr as fayth, hope, pacyence, ryght wyſenes, peace, and loue, be vnſepe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable, and that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can haue the one without the other, lyke as fayth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of the worde of god, and hope co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of fayth, &amp; charite ſpryngeth of them both. For the worde of God is quycke &amp; mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty in operacyon, &amp; ſharper then any two edged ſwerde, and entreth thorowe eue<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the deuydynge a ſounder of the ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:9646:11"/> and the ſpyryte, and of the ioyntes and the mary, &amp; iudgeth the thoughtes and the intentes of the hert, neyther is there any creature inuiſible in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of hym. Hebre .iiij. So that we can not do, nor yet obtayne any goodneſſe without the wyll of God, in whome muſt be alwayes our hope. Thus may you marke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faith beleueth onely in god, and in his worde, hope truſteth after it that is promyſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde, charyte doth good vnto her neyghbour, thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue that it hath to God and his worde. Nowe when you wyll take vpon you, to lyue after goddes worde, ſo haue you tyſynge agaynſt you many ennemyes (to make you to forſake god) as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, the fleſſhe, &amp; the deuyll, but fayth loketh to God and his worde, hope loketh vnto his gyft and rewarde, charyte loketh on her neyghbours pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte. Therfore bretherne yf we be ſtablyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed in the trueth of gods worde, it wyll make vs, that we ſhall not be ydle, no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unfruytefull.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9646:11"/>
            <p>THerfore (ſayth Chryſte) be of good there, for yf the worlde hate you, y<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowe, that he hated me before he hated you. &amp;c. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xv. The worlde is nothynge els, but the hole companye of carnall men, whiche lyue after the luſtes of the fleſſhe and blode, beynge deade in treſpaſſe and ſynne, as natural chyldren of the wrath of god, and be frembe from the teſtamentꝭ of promyſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in chryſte beynge without hope, yee and without god in this worlde, whiche walke in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyties of theyr owne myndes, blynde in theyr vnderſtandynge thorowe they ygnorancy, and beynge paſt repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce haue gyuen themſelues ouer vnto wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe, for the ymagynacyon of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hert, is euyl from the very youth of hym contynually. Ge. vj. viij. What is more wycked, then the thynge that fleſſhe and blode hath ymagyned. Eccle. xvij. For <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which is hyghly eſtymed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge men, i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bhominable in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of god. Lu. xvj. <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t god ſo loued the worlde, that he hath
<pb facs="tcp:9646:12"/> gyuen his onely ſone, that none that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in hym ſhuld peryſſhe, but ſhuld ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue euerlaſtinge lyfe. For god ſent not his ſone in to the worlde to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, but that the worlde throughe hym myghte be ſaued. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleueth on hym, ſhall not be condempned. But he that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leued not, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned all redy, bycauſe he beleueth not in the name of the onely ſone of god. And this is the condempna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that lyght is come into the worlde and the men loued darkenes more then light, bycauſe theyr dedes were euyl. &amp;c. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij. Se therfore that ye loue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, neyther the thynges that are in the worlde, yf any man loue the worlde, the loue of the father is not in hym. For he that is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde (as the luſt of the fleſhe, the luſt of the iyes, and the pryde of goodes) is not of the father, but of the worlde. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde vanyſſheth away, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> luſt therof i. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ij. Who ſoeuer wyll be a frende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, is made th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enemye of God. Ia. iiij. For it cann<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9646:12"/> ſtande togyther, that a man maye be a frende of God and the worlde both, yf a man wyl haue frendſhip with the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, ſo muſt he conſent with the worlde in the wyckednes of the worlde, whoſe gyft and rewarde is none other, then ſynne, death, hell, &amp; dampnacyon. Nowe when the righteous knoweth al this, ſtrayght waye flyeth he to god with all his herte ſoule, and mynde, and leueth the world<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſayinge: Adewe all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath deceaued me Adew worlde with all thy vayne deſyres and pleaſures. I went aſtraye as I the ſought, I was deceyued as I the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, I was ful blynde, as I the loued, I was not right mynded, as I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſed, I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortleſſe, as I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broked, I was fremb<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, as I the ſerued, I was in death when I with the lyued, I was out of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yet, as I y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſawe, I was full of ſorowe when thou rewardeſt me not, I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſatyſfyed of thy gyftes, I was leade <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way, with thy myrth and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. Oh thy wyſdome is folyſſhenes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:9646:13"/> god, thy glory is but a flower of the feelde, or haye; thy laughynge is deceyte, thy beaute is ſtynkynge, thy rycheſſe is not durable, thy counceyll bryngeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyetnes, thy reward is deth, thy myrth endeth with ſorowe and payne, he that doth the ſeruyce, leaſeth his owne ſoule, there came neuer good vnto hym that lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the, there was neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte to hym, that ſoughte any at the, he was neuer good that pleaſed the, there was neuer done ryght mery, that reioyſed in the, he was neuer wel that was ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the, there cam neuer good to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> folowed the, there was neuer none that deſyred frendſhyp with the that knewe the wel, thou bryngeſt all them out of the ryght waye that loue the, thy loue is not iuſt nor vpryght, thy dealynge is all deceyte, Oh howe happy is he that neuer ſought the, but bleſſyd be he which hath his lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de god for his hope, and that ſeketh god with all his herte, ſoule, and mynde, fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of deth in to lyfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9646:13"/>
            <p>ANother enemy is the fleſſhe, whoſe dedes are theſe, aduoutry, fornyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, vnclennes, wantonnes, ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, wytchecraftꝭ, hatred, variaunce, wrath, ſtryfe, ſedycyon, ſectes, enuyinge, murther, dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, gloteny, vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall luſte, couetouſneſſe, and ſuche lyke. Ga. v. Col. iij. which foloweth after fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe, for we are all without vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, rude, &amp; vnhanſom in matters belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge to Goddes glorye, and oure ſouls helth, &amp; be yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde man of Adam, &amp; are all togyther fleſſhe, as ſayth Chryſt what that is borne of fleſſhe is fleſſhe. Yf that we thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt be not borne a new. Fleſſhe is alſo called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy nature of man, as lyfe, ſoule, reaſon, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge, frewyl, with the chefe and hygheſt powers that man hath, yf he be without the holy Ghoſte, for ſuch a man ſuch a body of ſynne, whiche can alſo do none other then ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, howe goodly that he doth ſhyne, &amp; name hym ſelfe, docter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſon, or preeſt. &amp;c. We knowe (ſayeth
<pb facs="tcp:9646:14"/> ſaynt Paule) that the fleſſhely mynde is enmyte agaynſt god, for it is not obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the lawe of God neyther can be, ſo that they which are gyuen to the fleſſhe, can not pleaſe god, we knowe that euery man is tempted, drawen away, and enti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced of his owne concupycence, and when this concupycence and luſt hath concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſhe bryngeth forth ſynne, and ſynne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is fynyſſhed bringeth forth death Ro. vij. Then let vs gyue oure ſelues to prayer, calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſpryte of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupyſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce raygne not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our mortal bodyes, euer knowleging w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a meke hert our iniquities to our father which is in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for he is faythful &amp; iuſt to remit vs our ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, &amp; to purge vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all euyls, by the blode of Ieſu chryſt his ſone. Amen.</p>
            <p>THe thyrde ennemye and pryncypall is the deuyll, whiche tempted, and begyled Eue in Paradyſe thorowe his ſucrelite .ij. Co. xj. Alſo the great dragon that olde ſerpent called the deuyll and ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thanas,
<pb facs="tcp:9646:14"/> which deceyueth all the worlde. Re. xii. Thus oure aduerſary the deuyll as a roryng lyon, walketh aboute, ſekyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge whom he may deuoure .i. Peter .v. He blyndeth the myndes of them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not, leſt the lyghte of the gloryous goſpell of Chryſt, which is the ymage of God, ſhulde ſhyne vnto them .ii. Cor. iiij. He taketh the worde of god out of theyr hertes, leſt they ſhulde beleue, &amp; be ſaued Mat. xiii. Luc. viii. He preuenteth them he corrupteth theyr wyttes .ii. Cor. ii.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> He worketh in the chyldren of vnbelefe Ephe. ii. He accuſeth mankynde before god, and the power of his Chryſte, day and nyght. Reu. xii. He chaungeth hym ſelfe in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faſſhyon of an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel of lyght that is to ſaye Sathan hath made h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m ſelfe, as thoughe he were the true me<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenger, or preacher of gods worde, who <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e (neuertheleſſe) can ſpeake none other but lyes, for he is a lyer, and the father therof, &amp; as many as be falſe preachers <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd teachers, are not better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſathan
<pb facs="tcp:9646:15"/> hym ſelfe is. Therfore put on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armour of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may ſtande ſtedfaſt agaynſt the crafty aſſautes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl, &amp; agaynſt the wyckednes of your ennemyes. Take to you the ſhelde of fayth, wherwith ye maye quenche all the fyry dartes of the wycked. Withſtande the deuyll, ſo ſhall he fly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you. Iaco. iiii. For Chryſt hath put downe hym that had lordeſhyp ouer death, that is to ſay the deuyll. Hebre. ii. Chryſt hath delyuered vs from the lawe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuyll, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hell. Let vs not gyue place to his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but kepe faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y our profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for fayth receyueth god, hope receyueth his rewarde, charyte lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth her neyghbour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a glad herte. Let <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s therfore go boldely to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeate of grace <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r fayth ꝑteyneth to god onely, &amp; chary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to her neyghbour, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we all may fynde grace &amp; mercy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord our god, to with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyous of the deuyll, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be not ouercome w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his fayre flateryng which bryngeth eternall dampnacyon.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprynted by me Robert wyer.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9646:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
